Mss.Rec.13 Mss.Rec.13
American Philosophical Society
Material on Iroquois Dialects and Languages
1950
Mss.Rec.13
American Philosophical Society
7.0 Reel(s)
This collections consists of texts in several Iroquoian languages (Cayuga, Cherokee, Mohawk, Oneida, Onondaga, Seneca, Tuscarora) recorded and played back to other speakers to test the mutual intelligibility of the languages for various speakers. The recordings comprise numerous texts in these languages, administered mutual intelligibility tests, stories, and conversations, all predominantly untranslated. Originally recorded on wire in the fall of 1950 at various locations in the United States and Canada. Later copied to sound tape reels. The native consultants involved in these recordings are as follows. The Cayuga language consultant was Jane Owl, recorded at Cattaraugus Indian Reservation (N.Y.) The Cherokee consultant was David Owl, recorded at Cattaraugus Indian Reservation (N.Y.) The Mohawk consultants were Ernest Benedict and Sadie Curlyhead, recorded at Saint Regis Mohawk Indian Reservation (N.Y.), and Ernest Benedict and Mr. & Mrs. Charles Benedict, recorded at Cornwall, Ontario. The Oneida consultants were Harry Antone, Betsy Antone, Rosa Antone, Billy Antone, and Mr. & Mrs. Chapman Schanandoah, recorded at the Onondaga Indian Reservation (N.Y.), and Albert Christian, recorded at Nedrow (N.Y.) The Onondaga consultants were Louis Lyons, recorded at the Cattaraugus Indian Reservation (N.Y.), and George Thomas, Jr., Percy Smoke, Thomas Lewis, Pat Homer, and Floyd Henhawk, recorded at the Onondaga Indian Reservation (N.Y.) The Seneca consultants were as follows: Annie Lyons, recorded at the Cattaraugus Indian Reservation (N.Y.); a Mr. & Mrs. Smith, recorded at the Oneida Nation of the Thames in southwestern Ontario; Richard Johnny John, Colline Johnny John, Amos Johnny John, Lena Snow, Kenneth Snow, Albert Jones, Hubert Cusick, Lynn Dowdy, Henry Redeye, Elver Jacobs, and Mr. & Mrs. Laurence Jimerson, recorded at the Allegany Indian Reservation (N.Y.); Jesse Cornplanter and Solon Skye, recorded at the Tonawanda Indian Reservation (N.Y.) The Tuscarora consultants were Nellie Gansworth and William Mt. Pleasant, recorded at the Tuscarora Indian Reservation (N.Y.)
7 sound tape reels (4 hr., 25 min.): analog, 3 3/4 ips, half track, mono; 7 in.
Antone, Betsy
Antone, Billy
Antone, Harry
Antone, Rosa
Benedict, Charles, Mrs.
Benedict, Charles
Benedict, Ernest
Christian, Albert
Cornplanter, Jesse J.
Curlyhead, Sadie
Cusick, Herbert
Dowdy, Lynn
Gansworth, Nellie
Henhawk, Floyd
Hickerson, Harold, 1923-
Hickerson, Nancy Parrott
Jacbos, Elver
Jimerson, Laurence, Mrs.
Jimerson, Laurence
Johnny John, Amos
Johnny John, Colline
Johnny John, Richard
Jones, Albert
Lewis, Thomas
Lyons, Annie
Lyons, Louise
Mt. Pleasant, William
Owl, David
Owl, Jane
Redeye, Henry
Schanandoah, Chapman, Mrs.
Schanandoah, Chapman
Skye, Solon
Smoke, Percy
Snow, Kenneth
Snow, Lena
Thomas, George, Jr.
Turner, Glen D.
Related Archival Materials
A table of contents, detailed notes, and texts used in this recording collection are available in the Franz Boas Collection of Materials for American Linguistics (Mss.497.3.B63c I1.3).
Existence and Lcoation of Originals note
Originals tapes at the Archives of Traditional Music, Indiana University.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Deposited from the American Indian Institute, Indiana University, through C.F. Voegelin, 1952.
Cayuga language; Cherokee language; Indians of North America--Languages--Mutual intelligibility; Iroquoian languages; Mohawk language; Oneida language; Onondaga language; Seneca language; Sound recordings; Tuscarora language; Typology (Linguistics)
- Audio recordings
  - Cherokee Text #1, 1950; 01-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:06; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Owl, David; Turner, Glen D.
    Scope and Contents note
    Recording begins at slow speed, but corrects itself. Original tapes in Archives of Languages of the World, Indiana University.
    Existence and Location of Originals note
    This file is a compressed, digitized version of the original. The APS Library maintains the original format (Sound tape reel) as well as an uncompressed digitized version of this recording.
    Cattaraugus Indian Reservation (N.Y.); Cherokee Indians; Cherokee language; Indians of North America--Languages--Mutual intelligibility; Iroquoian languages--Dialects; Typology (Linguistics)
  - Cherokee Text #2, 1950; 01-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:55; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Owl, David; Turner, Glen D.
    Original tapes in Archives of Languages of the World, Indiana University.
  - Cherokee Text #3, 1950; 01-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:07; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Owl, David; Turner, Glen D.
  - Cayuga Text #1, 1950; 01-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:26; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Owl, Jane; Turner, Glen D.
    Cattaraugus Indian Reservation (N.Y.); Cayuga Indians; Cayuga language; Indians of North America--Languages--Mutual intelligibility; Iroquoian languages--Dialects; Typology (Linguistics)
  - Conversation in Onondaga and Seneca, 1950; 01-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:05:33; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Lyons, Annie; Lyons, Louis; Turner, Glen D.
    Cattaraugus Indian Reservation (N.Y.); Indians of North America--Languages--Mutual intelligibility; Iroquoian languages--Dialects; Onondaga language; Seneca language; Typology (Linguistics)
  - Oneida Conversation #1, 1950; 01-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:09:52; Antone, Betsy; Antone, Billy; Antone, Harry; Antone, Rosa; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Turner, Glen D.
    Includes singing. Original tapes in Archives of Languages of the World, Indiana University.
    Indians of North America--Languages--Mutual intelligibility; Iroquoian languages--Dialects; Oneida Indians; Oneida language; Onondaga Indian Reservation (N.Y.); Typology (Linguistics)
  - Oneida Conversation #2, 1950; 01-07; 1.0 .mp3; 00:08:34; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Schanandoah, Chapman, Mrs.; Schanandoah, Chapman; Turner, Glen D.
  - Mohawk Conversation #1, 1950; 01-08; 1.0 .mp3; 00:08:19; Benedict, Ernest; Curlyhead, Sadie; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Turner, Glen D.
    Indians of North America--Languages--Mutual intelligibility; Iroquoian languages--Dialects; Mohawk Indians; Mohawk language; Saint Regis Mohawk Indian Reservation (N.Y.); Typology (Linguistics)
  - Oneida Text #1, 1950; 01-09; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:26; Christian, Albert; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Turner, Glen D.
    Recorded at Onondaga Reservation. Original tapes in Archives of Languages of the World, Indiana University.
    Indians of North America--Languages--Mutual intelligibility; Iroquoian languages--Dialects; Nedrow (N.Y.); Oneida Indians; Oneida language; Typology (Linguistics)
  - Mohawk Text #1, 1950; 01-10; 1.0 .mp3; 00:05:06; Benedict, Charles, Mrs.; Benedict, Charles; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Turner, Glen D.
    Recorded at Cornwall Island, Ontario, Canada. Original tapes in Archives of Languages of the World, Indiana University.
    Cornwall (Ont.); Indians of North America--Languages--Mutual intelligibility; Iroquoian languages--Dialects; Mohawk Indians; Mohawk language; Typology (Linguistics)
  - Tuscarora Story #1, 1950; 01-11; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:16; Gansworth, Nellie; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Turner, Glen D.
    Indians of North America--Languages--Mutual intelligibility; Iroquoian languages--Dialects; Tuscarora Indians; Tuscarora language; Tuscarora Nation Reservation (N.Y.); Typology (Linguistics)
  - Tuscarora Story #2, 1950; 01-12; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:13; Gansworth, Nellie; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Turner, Glen D.
  - Seneca Story #1, 1950; 01-13; 1.0 .mp3; 00:13:11; Cornplanter, Jesse J.; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Turner, Glen D.
    Indians of North America--Languages--Mutual intelligibility; Iroquoian languages--Dialects; Seneca Indians; Seneca language; Tonawanda Indian Reservation (N.Y.); Typology (Linguistics)
  - Seneca Story #2, 1950; 01-14; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:47; Cornplanter, Jesse J.; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Turner, Glen D.
  - Seneca Story #3, 1950; 01-15; 1.0 .mp3; 00:04:12; Cornplanter, Jesse J.; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Turner, Glen D.
  - Seneca Story #4, 1950; 01-16; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:39; Cornplanter, Jesse J.; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Turner, Glen D.
  - Seneca Story #5, 1950; 01-17; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:48; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Skye, Solon; Turner, Glen D.
  - Seneca Story #6, 1950; 01-18; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:42; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Skye, Solon; Turner, Glen D.
  - Seneca Story #7, 1950; 01-19; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:02; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Skye, Solon; Turner, Glen D.
  - Seneca Conversation #1, 1950; 01-20; 1.0 .mp3; 00:05:27; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Johnny John, Colline; Johnny John, Richard; Turner, Glen D.
    Allegany Indian Reservation (N.Y.); Indians of North America--Languages--Mutual intelligibility; Iroquoian languages--Dialects; Seneca Indians; Seneca language; Typology (Linguistics)
  - Seneca Conversation #2, 1950; 01-21; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:53; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Snow, Kenneth; Snow, Lena; Turner, Glen D.
  - Seneca Conversation #3, 1950; 01-22; 1.0 .mp3; 00:16:23; Cusick, Hubert; Dowdy, Lynn; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Jacobs, Elver; Johnny John, Amos; Jones, Albert; Redeye, Henry; Turner, Glen D.
    Includes 8 social dance songs. Original tapes in Archives of Languages of the World, Indiana University.
  - Seneca Conversation #4, 1950; 01-23; 1.0 .mp3; 00:07:16; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Jimerson, Laurence, Mrs.; Jimerson, Laurence; Turner, Glen D.
    Cattaraugus Indian Reservation (N.Y.); Indians of North America--Languages--Mutual intelligibility; Iroquoian languages--Dialects; Seneca Indians; Seneca language; Typology (Linguistics)
  - Onondaga Conversation #1, 1950; 02-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:20:21; Henhawk, Floyd; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Homer, Pat; Lewis, Thomas; Smoke, Percy; Thomas, George, Jr.; Turner, Glen D.
    Indians of North America--Languages--Mutual intelligibility; Iroquoian languages--Dialects; Oneida language; Onondaga Indian Reservation (N.Y.); Onondaga Indians; Typology (Linguistics)
  - Tuscarora Text #3, 1950; 02-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:05:46; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Mt. Pleasant, William; Turner, Glen D.
  - Unidentified conversation, 1950; 02-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:01; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Turner, Glen D.
    Indians of North America--Languages--Mutual intelligibility; Iroquoian languages--Dialects; Typology (Linguistics)
  - Mohawk Word List, 1950; 03-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:08:37; Benedict, Ernest; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Turner, Glen D.
    Cornwall (Ont.); Indians of North America--Languages--Mutual intelligibility; Iroquoian languages--Dialects; Mohawk language; Typology (Linguistics)
  - Oneida Word List, 1950; 03-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:08:55; Antone, Betsy; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Turner, Glen D.
    Indians of North America--Languages--Mutual intelligibility; Iroquoian languages--Dialects; Oneida language; Onondaga Indian Reservation (N.Y.); Typology (Linguistics)
  - Cayuga Word List, 1950; 03-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:04:32; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Owl, Jane; Turner, Glen D.
    Cattaraugus Indian Reservation (N.Y.); Cayuga language; Indians of North America--Languages--Mutual intelligibility; Iroquoian languages--Dialects; Typology (Linguistics)
  - Onondaga Word List, 1950; 03-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:09:59; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Lyons, Louis; Turner, Glen D.
    Cattaraugus Indian Reservation (N.Y.); Indians of North America--Languages--Mutual intelligibility; Iroquoian languages--Dialects; Onondaga language; Typology (Linguistics)
  - Cherokee Word List, 1950; 03-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:12:49; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Owl, David; Turner, Glen D.
    Cattaraugus Indian Reservation (N.Y.); Cherokee language; Indians of North America--Languages--Mutual intelligibility; Iroquoian languages--Dialects; Typology (Linguistics)
  - Seneca Word List, 1950; 03-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:52; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Snow, Lena; Turner, Glen D.
    Allegany Indian Reservation (N.Y.); Indians of North America--Languages--Mutual intelligibility; Seneca language; Typology (Linguistics)
  - Tuscarora Word List, 1950; 03-07; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:39; Gansworth, Nellie; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Turner, Glen D.
    Indians of North America--Languages--Mutual intelligibility; Iroquoian languages--Dialects; Tuscarora language; Tuscarora Nation Reservation (N.Y.); Typology (Linguistics)
  - Text 1, 1950; 04-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:57; Cornplanter, Jesse J.; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Turner, Glen D.
  - Text 2, 1950; 04-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:38; Benedict, Ernest; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Turner, Glen D.
  - Text 3, 1950; 04-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:16; Gansworth, Nellie; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Turner, Glen D.
  - Text 4, 1950; 04-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:11; Antone, Betsy; Antone, Harry; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Turner, Glen D.
  - Text 5, 1950; 04-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:30; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Owl, Jane; Turner, Glen D.
  - Text 6, 1950; 04-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:48; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Owl, David; Turner, Glen D.
  - Text 7, 1950; 04-07; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:56; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Smoke, Percy; Turner, Glen D.
    Indians of North America--Languages--Mutual intelligibility; Iroquoian languages--Dialects; Onondaga Indian Reservation (N.Y.); Onondaga Indians; Onondaga language; Typology (Linguistics)
  - Text 8, 1950; 04-08; 1.0 .mp3; 00:05:11; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Lyons, Annie; Lyons, Louis; Turner, Glen D.
  - Text 1C, 1950; 05-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:29; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Skye, Solon; Turner, Glen D.
  - Text 5B, 1950; 05-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:37; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Owl, Jane; Turner, Glen D.
  - Text 7B, 1950; 05-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:39; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Smoke, Percy; Turner, Glen D.
    Recorded at Allegheny Reservation, Red House, N.Y. Original tapes in Archives of Languages of the World, Indiana University.
    Cattaraugus County (N.Y.); Indians of North America--Languages--Mutual intelligibility; Iroquoian languages--Dialects; Onondaga Indians; Onondaga language; Typology (Linguistics)
  - Text 3B, 1950; 05-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:35; Christian, Albert; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Turner, Glen D.
  - Text 2B, 1950; 05-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:32; Benedict, Charles; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Turner, Glen D.
  - Text 4A, 1950; 05-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:31; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Mt. Pleasant, William; Turner, Glen D.
  - Text 6B, 1950; 05-07; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:50; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Owl, David; Turner, Glen D.
  - Conversation between researchers, 1950; 05-08; 1.0 .mp3; 00:04:41; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Turner, Glen D.
    Contains researchers' discussion of recording conditions and logistics. Original tapes in Archives of Languages of the World, Indiana University.
  - Iroquoian speech, 1950; 06-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:45; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Turner, Glen D.
    Unidentified male speaker speaking a series of related syllables in an Iroquoian language. Original tapes in Archives of Languages of the World, Indiana University.
  - Text 1A, 1950; 06-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:36; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Snow, Kenneth; Snow, Lena; Turner, Glen D.
  - Text 1B, 1950; 06-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:48; Cornplanter, Jesse J.; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Turner, Glen D.
  - Text 1C, 1950; 06-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:30; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Skye, Solon; Turner, Glen D.
  - Text 2A, 1950; 06-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:48; Benedict, Ernest; Curlyhead, Sadie; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Turner, Glen D.
  - Text 2B, 1950; 06-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:32; Benedict, Charles; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Turner, Glen D.
  - Text 3A, 1950; 06-07; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:33; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Schanandoah, Chapman, Mrs.; Schanandoah, Chapman; Turner, Glen D.
  - Text 3B, 1950; 06-08; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:35; Christian, Albert; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Turner, Glen D.
  - Text 4A, 1950; 06-09; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:30; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Mt. Pleasant, William; Turner, Glen D.
  - Text 4B, 1950; 06-10; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:03; Gansworth, Nellie; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Turner, Glen D.
  - Text 5B, 1950; 06-11; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:28; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Owl, Jane; Turner, Glen D.
  - Text 6B, 1950; 06-12; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:48; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Owl, David; Turner, Glen D.
  - Text 7A, 1950; 06-13; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:33; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Lyons, Annie; Lyons, Louis; Turner, Glen D.
    Cattaraugus Indian Reservation (N.Y.); Indians of North America--Languages--Mutual intelligibility; Iroquoian languages--Dialects; Onondaga Indians; Onondaga language; Typology (Linguistics)
  - Text 7B, 1950; 06-14; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:39; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Smoke, Percy; Turner, Glen D.
  - Summary of research, 1950; 07-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:27; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-
    Cayuga language; Mohawk language; Oneida language; Seneca language; Tuscarora language
  - Mr. and Mrs. Peter Smith: Test 1, 1950; 07-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:12:55; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Smith, Mr.; Smith, Mrs.; Turner, Glen D.
    Records the responses of participants after having heard played-back recordings of texts in various languages. Part of a study of the mutual intelligibilty of Iroquois languages. The languages of the texts are Seneca, Mohawk, Oneida, Tuscarora, Cayuga, Cherokee, Onondaga. The recordings that were played to the partipants are Text 1 through Text 8 from this same collection. Program runs slightly fast. Original tapes in Archives of Languages of the World, Indiana University.
    Cayuga language; Mohawk language; Oneida Indian Reserve No. 41 (Ont.); Oneida language; Seneca language; Tuscarora language
  - Mr. and Mrs. Peter Smith: Test 3, 1950; 07-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:12:10; Hickerson, Harold, 1923-; Hickerson, Nancy Parrott; Smith, Mr.; Smith, Mrs.; Turner, Glen D.
    Records the responses of participants after having heard played-back recordings of texts in various languages. Part of a study of the mutual intelligibilty of Iroquois languages. The languages of the texts are Seneca, Mohawk, Oneida, Tuscarora, Cayuga, Cherokee, Onondaga. The recordings that were played to the partipants are (in order) Text 5B, 1C, 7B, 3B, 2B, 4A, and 6B from this same collection. Program runs slightly fast. Original tapes in Archives of Languages of the World, Indiana University.